<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Portfolio for Logan Langdon</title>
    <link>https://leauxgan1.github.io</link>
    <description>Portfolio for Logan Langdon - Blog</description>
    <generator>Zine -- https://zine-ssg.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 23:33:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Datastar Retrospective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This second post is mainly here to show you that you can also create single file posts for convenience. The first post contains more interesting content.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://zine-ssg.io/docs/supermd/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the official SuperMD docs&lt;/a&gt; to know how to &lt;em&gt;style&lt;/em&gt; your content.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
        <link>https://leauxgan1.github.io/blog/second-post/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://leauxgan1.github.io/blog/second-post/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Implications of HTML Rendering Strategies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I remember first learning about web development through online resources such as W3 Schools and freecodecamp.org and understanding that there is a linear progression to advancing your expertise in web development. First, as with any domain in computing, start with the basics; HTML, CSS and some inline scripts to get some unique behavior. Then, once you are comfortable with those tools, move on to something more robust, like Frontend Development Libraries. Thankfully freecodecamp does mention some more simple tools first, such as Bootstrap, SASS and JQuery which are more reasonable steps toward improved development practices. Soon after, however, SPA frameworks are also introduced such as React and after that Redux to share state within React. I remember that this didn’t feel like that much of a difference from using JS proper, mostly because I didn’t understand the implications that React imposes, namely using Client Side Rendering.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;A beginner’s perspective of the world of web development&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When starting out with web fundamentals, there is usually no conception of the server. This is done intentionally to reduce the initial load of complexity for the learner. This is amplified by the common format of game-ifying programming lessons into bite-sized pieces that feel more satisfying to accomplished. This culminates in the limited perspective of how an app works in its totality. The world is:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;My markdown which gives structure&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My stylesheets which provide, well, style&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;My scripts which do everything else&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;(Maybe) A server which gives some info&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given this perspective, it seems like React is a great choice solely for the ability to have components which is otherwise not possible (it would seem) for the new webdev.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The true scope of the Webapp&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once more experience has been gained and projects using these technologies are experimented with, it quickly becomes evident that this perspective is not sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The main issue that presents itself is the sheer amount of fetching, either with the Fetch API or libraries like Axios, that is required to put into components.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then again, if this fetching is minimized and more state is managed on the client, that state is often out of date as it represents the state of the server at the time of the initial fetch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;These are problems that any SPA framework would have, but React has some extra ones as well. Namely, component lifecycles and rerenders that are unintuitive for the procedural-minded developer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once we are given some time to zoom out, we see the true scope from the bottom-up:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A database storing persistent state our users are interested in&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A cache ensuring we don’t overcrowd our datastore with unnecessary reads.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A backend which routes pipelines of data to any client asking for it&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Middleware that validates requests and packages results.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Load balancers to make sure we don’t overcrowd our server&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;A frontend defined with HTML, CSS and JS for interactivity&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Given this perspective, we can see that our frontend framework is actually the furthest thing from the source of truth, making it extremely risky to use it assuming it is.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The Misapplication of 80/20&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The assumption that many frontend frameworks seem to make is that a majority of the computation should be on the frontend to maximize responsiveness and the minority is sending information from the backend to the client.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This may be the case for some webapps, such as live dashboards and online games, but the ratio is flipped for the average case, even assuming you want responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem with the former assumption is twofold:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;The dilution of state responsibility between the server and client makes apps more difficult to manage and keep state up to date.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The concentration of code on the frontend can reduce responsiveness when more intensive tasks could be done on a more performant backend.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Because of this, it would seem our frontends should be lightweight and simply handle easy and superficial tasks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can create some solutions for this purpose:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;JQuery &amp; Webcomponents&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;h2&gt;HATEOAS and SPAs Philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Luckily we have a different solution available, Hypermedia!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Logan&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
        <link>https://leauxgan1.github.io/blog/first-post/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://leauxgan1.github.io/blog/first-post/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
